<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!--
    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
    or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information
    regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
    to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
    "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.
	   
-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Communicating Between Pages: pageFlowScope</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Communicating Between Pages">
      <p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <a href="#Overview">Overview</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="#pageFlowScope">pageFlowScope</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="#tr:setActionListener">tr:setActionListener</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="#Bookmarking support">Bookmarking support</a>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </p>
    </section>
    <section name="Overview">
      <p>
One of the most common questions about application development
in JavaServer Faces (JSF) is how to communicate values between pages.  For example,
how do I pick one row out of a table, and show it on a second
page to start editing it?  How do I take search criteria entered
on one page, and show the results on a second?  Both of these 
(and many other common web application scenarios) require some
mechanism to pass a value from one page to another.   The two
common solutions in JSF have been storing values on the
request or on the session.  Both can be made to work, but
both have major limitations.  Apache Trinidad introduces a new "pageFlowScope"
that seeks to offer the best of both.  (This support is built entirely
off of existing, specified hooks in the Faces specification, and
is not based on proprietary extensions.  If there
is interest from the rest of the Faces expert group, we would be
very interested in contributing this back into the specification.)
      </p>
      <p>
When using a request-scope value, an action listener might take
the ID of that table row, or the collection of search results,
and place that object into request scope, either directly:
     </p>
<source>
      FacesContext context = FacesContext.getCurrentInstance();
      context.getExternalContext().getRequestMap().put("search", criteria);
</source> <p>
... or indirectly, by storing it as a property of a request-scoped
<code>&lt;managed-bean&gt;</code>.  This works, but has some significant drawbacks:
<ul>
<li>The <code>&lt;navigation-case&gt;</code> used for page navigation can't
specify <code>&lt;redirect/&gt;</code>, because that would lead to 
a client-side redirect, which would mean the second page
gets rendered on a new request.  <code>&lt;redirect/&gt;</code> is very
useful for supporting bookmarking and better Back button
support.</li>

<li>Even if you don't redirect, the second page still has the
problem of making sure that this request-scoped value is
still available for its own purposes when it posts back.</li>
</ul>
     </p>
     <p>
To avoid these problems, developers might use session-scoped
variables instead.  This fixes both of those problems, but
adds new ones:
<ul>
<li>A single user cannot have two windows open simultaneously;  session-scoped
variables are global to the user.  So, for instance, a user could
not work with two different search results simultaneously.
</li>

<li>
Back button support is highly limited, since navigating back
can't magically restore the session to its old state.
</li>
</ul>
     </p>
     <p>
Finally, both session- and request-scoped parameters make bookmark
support completely hopeless;  similarly, they make it very difficult
if you need to support emailing a link to a page.  The URL does not
and cannot contain enough information on its own to show a target page.
     </p>
     <p>
Apache Trinidad offers a new scope - "pageFlowScope" - that aims to solve
all of these problems.  It's a very new and experimental feature,
and we're interested in feedback on how well it addresses the
problem (it's not a panacea - some limitations are described below).
     </p>
    </section>
    <section name="pageFlowScope">
<p>
In addition to the standard JSF scopes - applicationScope,
sessionScope, and requestScope - Apache Trinidad adds a new scope,
pageFlowScope.  Values added to this scope will automatically continue
to be available as the user continues navigating from one page to
another.  This is true even if you use <code>&lt;redirect/&gt;</code>.
But unlike session scope, these values are only visible in
the current "page flow".  If the user opens up a new window
and starts navigating, that series of windows will have
their own page flow, and values stored in each window will
remain independent.  And clicking the Back button will
automatically reset the page flow scope to its original
state. 
</p>
<p>
From the JSF EL, it looks just like any other scope:
<source>
     &lt;h:outputText value="#{pageFlowScope.someKey}"/>
</source>
<b>Note:</b>  As you can see in this example, "pageFlowScope"
is supported for <b>all</b> JSF components, not just Apache Trinidad
components.
</p>
<p>

From Java code, you can access the page flow scope as a
<code>java.util.Map</code> off of the <code>RequestContext</code>
API.  (Despite its name, this class does not extend
<code>FacesContext</code>, but it is a similar idea.)

<source>
import org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.context.RequestContext;

public class BackingBean
{
  public String myAction()
  {
    Object someValue = ...;

    RequestContext requestContext = RequestContext.getCurrentInstance();
    requestContext.getPageFlowScope().put("someKey", someValue);

    return "myOutcome";
  } 
}
</source>
</p>
     <subsection name="Example:">
<p>
  Let's start with an <code>&lt;h:dataTable&gt;</code> showing some data:
</p>
<source>
            &lt;h:dataTable var="employee" value="#{....}"&gt;
              ...
              &lt;h:column&gt;
                &lt;h:outputText value="#{employee.name}"/>
              &lt;h:column&gt;
              &lt;h:column&gt;
                &lt;h:outputText value="#{employee.id}"/>
              &lt;h:column&gt;
            &lt;/h:dataTable&gt;
</source>
<p>
Now, we want to show more information about that employee on
another detail page.  We'll add a commandButton, and tie it
to a "showEmployee" action in our backing bean:
<source>
            &lt;h:dataTable var="employee" value="#{....}"&gt;
              ...
              &lt;h:column&gt;
                &lt;h:outputText value="#{employee.name}"/>
              &lt;h:column&gt;
              &lt;h:column&gt;
                &lt;h:outputText value="#{employee.id}"/>
              &lt;h:column&gt;
              &lt;h:column&gt;
                &lt;h:commandButton value="Show more"
                                 action="#{backingBean.showEmployee}"/>
              &lt;h:column&gt;
            &lt;/h:dataTable&gt;
</source>
</p>
<p>Now all we've got to do is write the code for <code>showEmployee()</code>.
First, we'll find the current employee, and then we'll put it onto
the page flow scope.
<source>
import javax.faces.context.FacesContext;
import org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.context.RequestContext;

public class BackingBean
{
  public String showEmployee()
  {
    // Find the current employee.  I'll just look on the VariableResolver.
    // (A lot of code out on the web manually creates a ValueBinding
    // for "#{employee}" and executes it - this is a much simpler approach!
    FacesContext context = FacesContext.getCurrentInstance();
    Employee emp = (Employee)
       context.getVariableResolver().resolveVariable(context, "employee");
    if (emp == null)
      return "error";
   
    RequestContext requestContext = RequestContext.getCurrentInstance();
    requestContext.getPageFlowScope().put("detailEmployee", emp);

    // Navigate to whatever page handles the "showEmployee" outcome
    return "showEmployee";
  }
}
</source>
</p>

<p>If you owned the code for "Employee", you might
consider moving <code>showEmployee()</code> directly onto
<code>Employee</code>, in which case the code would simply be:

<source>
import org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.context.RequestContext;

public class Employee
{
  ...
  public String showEmployee()
  {
    RequestContext requestContext = RequestContext.getCurrentInstance();
    // No need to find the employee - it's "this"
    requestContext.getPageFlowScope().put("detailEmployee", this);

    // Navigate to whatever page handles the "showEmployee" outcome
    return "showEmployee";
  }
}
</source>
... but as you'll see below, there's an even easier way.
</p>
<p>
Now, on our detail page, we can just refer to the
"pageFlowScope.detailEmployee" object:
<source>
  &lt;h:panelGrid columns="2"&gt;
    &lt;h:outputText value="Name:"/&gt;
    &lt;h:outputText value="#{pageFlowScope.detailEmployee.name}"/&gt;

    &lt;h:outputText value="Employee ID:"/&gt;
    &lt;h:outputText value="#{pageFlowScope.detailEmployee.id}"/&gt;

    &lt;h:outputText value="Salary"/&gt;
    &lt;h:outputText value="#{pageFlowScope.detailEmployee.salary}"&gt;
      &lt;f:convertNumber type="currency"/&gt;
    &lt;h:outputText&gt;
  &lt;/h:panelGrid&gt;
</source>
</p>
<p>
That's all there is to it.  The detail page does need to know where to
look for the incoming value.  The
"detailEmployee" object also persists automatically at pageFlowScope
if there were a "Show Even More Details" button on this detail page.
</p>
     </subsection>
     <subsection name="Limitations of pageFlowScope">
<p>
Before moving on, there are, however, a number of limitations of pageFlowScope.
</p>
<p>First, since pageFlowScope is not part of the standard JSF 
specification, a couple of the niceties of standard scopes
can't be supported:
<ul>

<li>EL expressions do not automatically look into pageFlowScope;  if you wish to locate a page flow-scoped value, you must
include "pageFlowScope." (For instance, in the previous example, we couldn't write "#{employeeDetail}" - we had to write "#{pageFlowScope.employeeDetail}".)</li>

<li>"page flow" cannot be used as a <code>&lt;managed-bean-scope&gt;</code>.  (But
the <code>&lt;value&gt;</code> of a <code>&lt;managed-property&gt;</code> can refer to
page flow-scoped values.) </li>

</ul>
</p>
<p>Second, because the original and detail pages have to agree on
the name of the page flow-scoped variable, they are more tightly
coupled than is ideal.
</p>
<p>
Finally, pageFlowScope never empties itself;  the only way 
to clear pageFlowScope is to manually force it to clear:
<source>
     RequestContext requestContext = RequestContext.getCurrentInstance();
     requestContext.getPageFlowScope().clear();
</source>
</p>
     </subsection>
    </section>

    <section name="tr:setActionListener">

<p>This code is easy, but to make coding even simpler, we provide a
new <code>ActionListener</code> tag that lets you code this style
without writing <em>any</em> Java code.  The
<code>&lt;tr:setActionListener&gt;</code> tag has two properties,
"from" and "to", and simply takes a value from the "from" attribute
and puts it where "to" says to put it.  Let's recode the last example
with this tag:
</p>
<source>
            &lt;h:dataTable var="employee" value="#{....}"&gt;
              ...
              &lt;h:column&gt;
                &lt;h:outputText value="#{employee.name}"/>
              &lt;h:column&gt;
              &lt;h:column&gt;
                &lt;h:outputText value="#{employee.id}"/>
              &lt;h:column&gt;
              &lt;h:column&gt;
                &lt;h:commandButton value="Show more" action="showEmployee"&gt;
                  &lt;tr:setActionListener from="#{employee}"
                                        to="#{pageFlowScope.employeeDetail}"/&gt;
                &lt;/h:commandButton&gt;
              &lt;h:column&gt;
            &lt;/h:dataTable&gt;
</source>

<p>And that's it!  No code is required in your backing bean at all
to implement this pattern.  Let's walk through how this page works
when the button is clicked:
<ol>
<li>An <code>ActionEvent</code> fires on the commandButton.  Since
it's inside a table row, the "employee" EL variable is pointing at
the current row.</li>
<li><code>ActionListeners</code> execute before any <code>"action"</code>
excute, so <code>&lt;tr:setActionListener&gt;</code> executes.</li>
<li><code>&lt;tr:setActionListener&gt;</code> retrieves the
   employee using the "#{employee}" EL expression.</li>
<li><code>&lt;tr:setActionListener&gt;</code> stores the 
   employee into page flow scope with the "#{pageFlowScope.employeeDetail}"
   EL expression.</li>
<li>Finally, the "action" executes with a static outcome - always
show the employee.  No backing bean is needed.</li>
</ol>
</p>
<p>Some may point out that this tag amounts to putting code in the UI,
and that is actually quite true.  It is a matter of personal taste
whether this style of coding is acceptable or not, but used sparingly,
it can greatly simplify reading and understanding page logic.  We
would never recommend using <code>&lt;tr:setActionListener&gt;</code>
to write values into a true model object. For example, you <em>could</em>
write:
<source>
            &lt;h:dataTable var="employee" value="#{....}"&gt;
              ...
              &lt;h:column&gt;
                &lt;h:outputText value="#{employee.name}"/>
              &lt;h:column&gt;
              &lt;h:column&gt;
                &lt;h:outputText value="#{employee.id}"/>
              &lt;h:column&gt;
              &lt;h:column&gt;
                &lt;h:commandButton value="Give Raise"&gt;
                  &lt;tr:setActionListener from="#{employee.salary + 500}"
                                        to="#{employee.salary}"/&gt;
                &lt;/h:commandButton&gt;
              &lt;h:column&gt;
            &lt;/h:dataTable&gt;
</source>
... but this style of coding mixes application logic directly
into your page.  This is all well and good for quick prototyping, but 
is very dangerous for writing production code that has to be maintained.
</p>

    </section>
    <section name="Bookmarking support">
<p>

The current implementation of pageFlowScope adds a single query
parameter to your URL, for example, "?_afPfm=4".  This token points into
internal structures stored by Apache Trinidad at session scope.  The
strategy allows pageFlowScope to store objects of any type, but does
nothing to help with bookmarking (the tokens are not persistent across
requests or users).  In future versions of Apache Trinidad, wemay
support an augmented strategy that will detect when pageFlowScope
contains nothing but primitive objects - such as strings,
<code>java.lang.Integers</code> - and automatically store
these values directly on the URL.  This can directly and 
transparently enable bookmarkability (especially if you use
<code>&lt;redirect/&gt;</code> in <code>&lt;navigation-case&gt;</code>)
for web developers using pageFlowScope with that restriction.
</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
