<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!--
    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
    or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information
    regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
    to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
    "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.
     
-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Configuring Apache Trinidad</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Configuring Apache Trinidad">
      <p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <a href="#trinidad-config.xml">trinidad-config.xml</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="#web.xml">web.xml</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="#Configuring Apache Trinidad for Performance">Configuring Apache Trinidad for Performance</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="#RequestContext">RequestContext</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="#The &quot;requestContext&quot; EL object">The 'requestContext' EL object</a>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </p>
    </section>
    <section name="trinidad-config.xml">
      <p>

      Apache Trinidad is configured with an
      <code>trinidad-config.xml</code> file. 
      If you need an
      <code>trinidad-config.xml</code> file then it must be placed in
      the WEB-INF directory of your web application.  This file has a
      very simple XML structure that relies on the JSF expression
      language (EL) for flexibility.  Each configurable property can be
      defined either inline with a static, constant value, or with a
      JSF EL expression that is re-evaluated on each request.
      </p>
      <subsection name="Example file">
<source><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<trinidad-config xmlns="http://myfaces.apache.org/trinidad/config">
  <!-- Enable debug output -->
  <debug-output>true</debug-output>

  <!-- Pick accessibility options based on a per-user managed bean -->
  <accessibility-mode>#{user.accessibilityMode}</accessibility-mode>

  <!-- A silly use of EL: English users get one appearance, -->
  <!-- others get another -->
  <skin-family>
    #{view.locale.language=='en' ?  'minimal' : 'customSkin'}
  </skin-family>
</trinidad-config>
]]>
</source>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Definition of subelements">
        <p>
        All <code>trinidad-config.xml</code> files must begin with
an <code>&lt;trinidad-config&gt;</code> element in the 
<code>http://myfaces.apache.org/trinidad/config</code> XML namespace.
The order of elements inside of <code>&lt;trinidad-config&gt;</code>
doesn't matter.
        </p>
        <subsection name="debug-output">
<p>
The <code>&lt;debug-output&gt;</code> element controls whether output is enhanced for
debugging.  Apache Trinidad adds a variety of features to aid in debugging,
including:
<ul>
<li>Automatically indenting output</li>
<li>Adding comments identifying which component was responsible
 for a block of HTML</li>
<li>Detecting unbalanced elements, repeated use of the
 same attribute in a single element, or other malformed markup
 problems</li>
<li>Detecting common HTML errors (like &lt;form&gt; tags
inside other &lt;form&gt; tags, &lt;tr&gt; or &lt;td&gt; tags
used in illegal locations, etc.)</li>
</ul>
</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="client-validation">
<p>
The <code>&lt;client-validation&gt;</code> element controls how client-side converters and validators are run.  Three values are supported:
<ul>
<li>"INLINE": validation is shown inline in a page (the default)</li>
<li>"ALERT": validation is shown in an Javascript alert</li>
<li>"DISABLED": validation is only handled on the server</li>
</ul>
</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="client-validation-disabled">
<p>
The <code>&lt;client-validation-disabled&gt;</code> element controls whether client side converters and validators are run.   This element is deprecated - please use &lt;client-validation&gt;.
</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="output-mode">
<p>
The <code>&lt;output-mode&gt;</code> element configures what "Output Mode"
Apache Trinidad is using.  Accepted values include:
<ul>
<li>"default" (or null): the default output mode</li>
<li>"printable": an output mode suitable for printable pages</li>
<li>"email": an output mode suitable for e-mailing a page's content</li>
</ul>
</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="skin-family">
<p>
The <code>&lt;skin-family&gt;</code> element configures the skin
to be used.  Accepted values include:
<ul>
<li>"minimal": a more minimal skin </li>
</ul>
Future releases of Apache Trinidad will define public APIs for extending
the set of available skins. Currently, you can create your own skin
by creating the skin definition in a file named trinidad-skins.xml.
See the Apache Trinidad demos for examples.
</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="accessibility-mode">
<p>
The <code>&lt;accessibility-mode&gt;</code> element defines the level
of accessibility support to be used.  Accepted values are:
<ul>
<li>"default": Output supports accessibility features</li>
<li>"inaccessible": Accessibility-specific constructs are stripped out to optimize output size</li>
<li>"screenReader": Accessibility-specific constructs are added to improve behavior under a screen reader (but
  may affect other users negatively)</li>
</ul>
</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="accessibility-profile">
<p>
The <code>&lt;accessibility-profile&gt;</code> element defines finer-grained
accessibility preferences than is possible to support with the acccessibility
mode.  Accepted values are:
</p>
<p>
<ul>
<li>"high-contrast": Indicates that the end user prefers high contrast-friendly content.</li>
<li>"large-fonts": Indicates that the end user prefers large fonts (larger fonts than the default font size provided by the skin).</li>
</ul>
</p>
<p>
Multiple values may be specified using whitespace to separate the values, eg:
</p>
<source><![CDATA[
  <!-- Enable both high-contrast and large-fonts content -->
  <accessibility-profile>high-contrast large-fonts</accessibility-profile>
]]>
</source>
<p>
Since accessibility preferences are user-specific, the accessibility-profile is typically bound, similar to the accessibility-mode.  The preferences specified by the accessibility profile can be used at runtime to tune both styles/icons defined by the skin as well as the content produced by Renderers.
</p>
<p>
The typical use case for the "high-contrast" preference is to work around issues relating to CSS background images when platform/browser high contrast features are enabled.  For example, when Windows High Contrast mode is enabled (Control Panel->Accessibility Options->Display->High Contrast->Use High Contrast), all background images are hidden.  In cases where background images are used to convey information, this information is lost to high contrast users.  The high-contrast accessibility profile option allows skin implementations to replace such background images with &lt;img&gt; element-based icons, thus avoiding the loss of information.
</p>
<p>
The typical use case for the "large-fonts" preference is to allow skins which specify small or non-scalable fonts (eg. px-based fonts on IE) to provide an alternate set of fonts for users who find the default fonts insufficient.
</p>
<p>
Note that at the moment, the Trinidad core renderers/skins do not yet take advantage of the accessibility profile preferences.  These properties are primarily provided for skin authors who wish to design skins which provide styles/icons optimized for high contrast/large font users.
</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="oracle-help-servlet-url">
<p>
The <code>&lt;oracle-help-servlet-url&gt;</code> element defines
an URL to an installation of Oracle Help for the Web (OHW).
Apache Trinidad supports OHW Version 2.0 as well as earlier versions.
Once this is configured, page content can be trivially attached
to any JSF tag that accepts an URL by using the "requestContext" EL
object. For example:
<source><![CDATA[
     <h:outputLink value="#{requestContext.helpTopic.someTopicID}">
       <h:outputText value="Get Help"/>
     </h:outputLink>]]></source>
</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="page-flow-scope-lifetime">
<p>
The <code>&lt;page-flow-scope-lifetime&gt;</code> element
controls the maximum number of pageFlowScope instances that will be
kept active at any one time.  The default is 15.  Unlike other
<code>&lt;trinidad-config&gt;</code> elements,
<code>&lt;page-flow-scope&gt;</code> lifetime does not support EL
expressions - it must be configured statically.
</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="time-zone">
<p>
The <code>&lt;time-zone&gt;</code> element defines the default
time zone used for date processing and date display.  Apache Trinidad
will attempt to default the time zone to the time zone used
by the client browser, but this property may be bound by
an EL expression to a <code>TimeZone</code> object if needed.
This value is used by <code>org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.converter.DateTimeConverter</code>
while converting strings to Date.
</p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection name="two-digit-year-start">
<p>
The <code>&lt;two-digit-year-start&gt;</code> element defines the 
year offset that should be used for parsing years with only two digits.
If it is not set, it is defaulted to year <code>1950</code>. This value is 
used by <code>org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.converter.DateTimeConverter</code>
while converting strings to Date. This property may also
be explicitly configured with an EL expression that returns 
Integer object if needed or can be directly harcoded to a integer value.
</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="right-to-left">
<p>
The <code>&lt;right-to-left&gt;</code> element defines whether pages
will be rendered in left-to-right mode (most languages) or
right-to-left mode (Arabic and Hebrew, for example).  While Apache Trinidad
will automatically pick the reading direction for you (sufficient for
the vast majority of developers), if you need a different
default association of language to reading direction you can use an EL
expression here that returns a Boolean object, or hardcode it to either 
"true" or "false".
</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="number-grouping-separator">
<p>
The <code>&lt;number-grouping-separator&gt;</code> element defines the
separator used for groups of numbers.  Apache Trinidad will automatically
derive the separator from the current locale, but it may also
be hardcoded or can be explicitly configured with an EL expression that returns
a Character object. If set, this value is used by 
<code>org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.converter.NumberConverter</code> while parsing 
and formatting.
</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="decimal-separator">
<p>

The <code>&lt;decimal-separator&gt;</code> element defines the
separator used for the decimal point.  Apache Trinidad will automatically
derive the separator from the current locale, but it may also
be hardcoded or can be explicitly configured with an EL expression that returns
a Character object. If set, this value is used by 
<code>org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.converter.NumberConverter</code> while parsing 
and formatting.

</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="currency-code">
<p>

The <code>&lt;currency-code&gt;</code> element defines the
ISO 4217 currency code used by default for formatting
currency fields when those fields do not specify an explicit
currency field via their converter. If this value is not specified
in the converter and is set here, then this value is used by 
<code>org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.converter.NumberConverter</code> while  
formatting. This value can be hardcoded or can be explicitly configured 
with an EL expression that returns a String object.

</p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection name="uploaded-file-processor">
<p>

The <code>&lt;uploaded-file-processor&gt;</code> element must
be the name of a class that implements the
<code>org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.webapp.UploadedFileProcessor</code>
interface.  This API is responsible for processing each individual
uploaded file as they come from the incoming request and making
its contents available for the rest of the request.  Most developers
will find the default <code>UploadedFileProcessor</code> sufficient
for their purposes, but applications that need to support uploading
very large files may improve their performance by immediately
storing files in their final destination, instead of requiring
Apache Trinidad to handle temporary storage during the request.
</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="formatting-locale">
<p>
The <code>&lt;formatting-locale&gt;</code> element is used by converters without
an explicit locale to format values.  Values for this follow the same format as
locale values in faces-config.xml (ie en_US).
</p>
        </subsection>
      </subsection>
    </section>
    <section name="web.xml">
<p>

Some Apache Trinidad configuration options are set instead with
<code>&lt;context-param&gt;</code> elements in your
<code>WEB-INF/web.xml</code>file.
</p>
<subsection name="org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.CACHE_VIEW_ROOT">
<p>
Enables or disables UIViewRoot caching;  defaults to true.
</p>
<p>
When "token" client-side state saving is enabled, Trinidad applies
an additional optimization by caching an entire UIViewRoot tree
with each token.  (Care has been taken to ensure that this
does not affect thread safety or session failover.)
This is a major optimization for AJAX-intensive
systems, as postbacks can be processed far more rapidly without
the need to reinstantiate the UIViewRoot tree.  However, 
it is known to interfere with some other JSF technologies.
In particular, the Apache MyFaces Tomahawk <code>saveState</code> component
does not work, and template text in Facelets may appear in duplicate.
This optimization can be disabled by setting this context parameter
to <code>false</code>.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.CLIENT_STATE_METHOD">
<p>
Chooses the type of client-side state saving used when client-side state saving is enabled (with the JSF standard <code>javax.faces.STATE_SAVING_METHOD</code>
parameter).  Two values are accepted:
<ul>
<li>"token":  the default, which stores page state in the session,
but persists a token to the client that lets Apache Trinidad disambiguate
the same page appearing multiple times.  Failover is supported.
</li>
<li>"all": stores all state in the client in a (potentially large)
hidden form field.  This matches the default behavior of the JSF reference
implementation, and can be useful for developers avoiding any
use of <code>HttpSession</code>.
</li>
</ul>
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.CLIENT_STATE_MAX_TOKENS">
<p>
In "token"-based client-side state saving, chooses how many tokens
should be preserved at any one time.  The default value is 15.
When this is exceeded, state will have effectively been "forgotten"
for the least recently viewed pages, which can impact users
that actively use the Back button or that have multiple windows
open simultaneously.  Developers building HTML applications that
rely heavily on frames will likely need to increase this value.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.USE_APPLICATION_VIEW_CACHE">
<p>
This configuration option enables an optimized strategy for caching some
view state at an application level, which significantly improves
scalability.  However, it makes it harder to develop (updates to
pages will not be noticed until the server is restarted), and in
some rare cases cannot be used for some pages.  See below for
more information about this option.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.DEBUG_JAVASCRIPT">
<p>
Apache Trinidad by default obfuscates the Javascript it delivers
to the client, as well as stripping comments and whitespace.
This dramatically reduces the size of our Javascript download,
but also makes it tricky to debug the Javascript.  This
flag can be set to true to turn off the obfuscation.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.DISABLE_CONTENT_COMPRESSION">
<p>
Apache Trinidad by default compresses the style class names inside the css that
is generated on the server.  However, when developing custom Trinidad skins, it
is much easier to work with the non-compressed style class names, which much more
directly relate to those used in the skin css file.  This flag can be set to turn
off automatic compression of style class names.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.CHECK_FILE_MODIFICATION">
<p>
If this parameter is enabled by setting to "true", Apache Trinidad will automatically
check the modification date of your JSPs and skinning CSS files, and discard saved
state when they change;  this makes development easier,
but adds overhead that should be avoided when your application
is deployed.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.ENABLE_LIGHTWEIGHT_DIALOGS">
<p>
Trinidad supports two dialog implementations.  The default implementation pops a new
browser window, but may be subject to popup blocking issues depending on the browser.
The alternative lightweight implementation uses a skinnable modal iframe that hovers 
over the existing page.  This flag can be set to turn on lightweight dialogs.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="File upload configuration">
<p>
For options affecting Apache Trinidad support of file uploads, please
see the <a href="fileUpload.html#Configuration">Configuration section
of the "Processing file uploads" document</a>.
</p>
</subsection>
    </section>
    <section name="Configuring Apache Trinidad for Performance">
<p>
When configuring Apache Trinidad for deployment, it is most critical
that debug options have been turned off.  Specifically:
<ul>
<li>&lt;debug-output&gt; should be removed or set to false.</li>
<li>org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.CHECK_FILE_MODIFICATION should be
   removed or set to false.
</li>
<li>org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.DEBUG_JAVASCRIPT should be removed or set to false.
</li>
</ul>
</p>

<p>In general, we strongly recommend that all clients use
client-side state saving with Apache Trinidad, not server-side 
state saving.  In practice, server-side state saving is
in fact somewhat more performant, but it suffers from
critical limitations that make it inadvisable in the
real world:  for example, there is no support for failover, 
the back button is only supported very, very poorly, and
users cannot properly show multiple windows at one time.
</p>

<p>When using client-side state saving with Apache Trinidad, the "token"
version of state-saving generally results in much better server
performance, because the CPU and I/O consumption is much lower.
However, "token"-based state saving does consume significantly more
memory, so memory-limited servers may in some cases benefit from using
"all" client-side state saving.</p>

<subsection name="The Application View Cache">
<p>
Apache Trinidad supports a special Application View Cache feature
that can increase scalability significantly.  However, it
can, in some unusual cases, break an otherwise functioning
application, so it is important to understand how it works
to understand whether it can be enabled for your pages.
</p>
<p>
In conventional JSF state saving, a page's UI state is saved 
the same way every time it is used.  It doesn't matter if 
state is being saved for an initial render of a page, or if 
state is being saved after a user has posted back to that page.
No two postbacks are necessarily the same - the user may
have entered entirely different data, navigated to
a different set of rows in the table, etc.  So, it is extremely
difficult to share state among postback requests.</p>

<p>However, most of the time, all initial renders of any
one page have exactly the same view state.  It doesn't matter
if the page is showing different data, or responding to
different query parameters, and so forth, because in JSF
those are conventionally accessed using the JSF expression
language (EL).  In JSF, what state saving remembers isn't the
result of evaluating an EL expression  - it's the EL expression
itself. So, when you see:
<source><![CDATA[
  <tr:outputText value="#{mybean.value}"/>
]]>
</source>
... all that's being saved is "#{mybean.value}", and that state is
the same no matter what that expression evaluates to.
</p>
<p>
The Application View Cache takes advantage of this, and caches
the state for these initial renders at an application scope.
Once the page has been viewed once, all users can reuse that
same state coming and going, saving some CPU (the CPU cost 
of saving the state each time) and more importantly the
memory overhead of keeping separate copies for each user.
State saving for postback is still separated per user,
but keep in mind that if the result of a postback is
that you navigate to a new page, the Application View
Cache is still in effect - it is only disabled when a postback
remains on a page (for example, because of a validation
failure).
</p>
<p>
Perhaps even more importantly, the Application View Cache enables
the use of web Proxy Caches in front of
your application server.  Token-based client-side state saving
defeats web proxy caches, because each user may have a different
token for any one page, defeating cacheability.  The Application
View Cache uses the same token across all users.
</p>
<p>All this should raise the question of why anyone would ever
not use the Application View Cache.  First, the technology
currently does not invalidate itself if the page is modified;
it requires a server restart.  This makes it difficult to use
during development.  Beyond this, however, there are some
JSF coding techniques that break the core assumption of
the Application View Cache - the assumption that the initial
view state of any one page is always the same, no matter who
views it:
<ol>
<li>Conditional tags that may not evaluate identically for each user</li>
<li>JSF components that pull EL results into page state</li>
</ol>
</p>
<p>
The following JSP includes two potential examples of the first problem:
<source><![CDATA[
  <c:if test="${user.locale.language='en'}">
    <h:outputText value="You're in an English locale"/>
  </c:if>

  <tr:selectOneListbox value="#{someValue}">
    <tr:forEach var="item" items="#{model.listOfItems}">
      <tr:selectItem value="#{item.value}" text="#{item.text}"/>
    </tr:forEach>
  </tr:selectOneListbox>
]]>
</source>
The &lt;c:if&gt; will show "You're in an English locale" if the locale's
language is English.  This means that in English, a user's version of
the page will have an extra component over users who aren't
using English;  the state will vary accordingly.  This sort of
problem can cleanly be resolved by using "rendered" instead of &lt;c:if&gt;,
which is always a recommended JSF best-practice:
<source><![CDATA[
    <h:outputText value="You're in an English locale"
                  rendered="#{user.locale.language == 'en'}"/>
]]>
</source>
The example using &lt;tr:forEach&gt; is less clear-cut, and 
less easily resolved.  If "model.listOfItems" always has the
same <em>number</em> of items when a page gets shown at first,
then there are no issues with this particular code sample.  But
if the number of items does vary from one user to another,  
then the page, as written, cannot support the Application View Cache.
In this particular case, there's also a simple workaround:
<source><![CDATA[
  <tr:selectOneListbox value="#{someValue}">
    <f:selectItems value="#{model.listOfSelectItems}"/>
  </tr:selectOneListbox>
]]>
</source>
</p>
<p>
In addition to problems with non-JSF tags that manipulate the
page, you can run into problems with some JSF tags that
directly manipulate page state.  A particular example of this
is the MyFaces &lt;x:save_state&gt; tag.  This tag will
evaluate an EL expression and save it directly as part
of the page's view state.  This is very nice functionality,
but it does directly and necessarily conflict with the
technique of the Application View Cache.
</p>


<p>At the moment, the Application View Cache can only
be enabled or disabled globally.  We are considering
adding support for disabling (or enabling) the view cache 
on a page-by-page basis.</p>

</subsection>

    </section>
    <section name="RequestContext">
<p>

All the properties defined in an <code>trinidad-config.xml</code>
file can be retrieved programatically with the
<code>org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.context.RequestContext</code> class.
One instance of this class exists per request, and it can
be retrieved using the static <code>getCurrentInstance()</code>
method (just like a <code>FacesContext</code>).  Despite the name,
<code>RequestContext</code> does <em>not</em> actually extend
<code>FacesContext</code>.
<source><![CDATA[
         RequestContext context = RequestContext.getCurrentInstance();

         // Get the time zone
         TimeZone zone = context.getTimeZone();

         // Are we in a right-to-left language?
         if (context.isRightToLeft())
         {
           ...
         }
]]>
</source>
In addition to the configuration properties described above, the
<code>RequestContext</code> object also exposes several properties
of type <code>java.util.Map</code> that help users write EL
expressions (see the next section for information on this 
use). For more information, see the Javadoc for this class.
</p>
    </section>
    <section name="The &quot;requestContext&quot; EL object">
<p>
Apache Trinidad exposes a number of values into the JSF EL language.  All
are grouped underneath a single "requestContext" EL variable.
</p>
      <subsection name="#{requestContext}">
<p>The EL expression <code>#{requestContext}</code> returns
the RequestContext object itself.</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="#{requestContext.helpTopic['foo']}">
<p>The EL expression <code>#{requestContext.helpTopic['foo']}</code> returns
an URL to the help topic "foo".  Before using this, you
must configure the <code>&lt;oracle-help-servlet-url&gt;</code> element
in <code>trinidad-config.xml</code>.
</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="#{requestContext.helpSystem['frontPage']}">
<p>The EL expression <code>#{requestContext.helpSystem['frontPage']}</code> returns
an URL to the front page of the help system.  Before using this, you
must configure the <code>&lt;oracle-help-servlet-url&gt;</code> element
in <code>trinidad-config.xml</code>.  (Other subproperties of
"helpSystem" may be added in the future.)
</p>
      </subsection>


      <subsection name="#{requestContext.colorPalette}">
<p>The EL expression <code>#{requestContext.colorPalette}</code> returns
a Map of color palettes, each of which is an array of
<code>java.awt.Color</code> objects.  Palette names include:
<ul>
<li>"web216": the 216 web-safe colors</li>
<li>"default49": a 49 color palette, including a fully transparent entry</li>
<li>"opaque49": a 49 color palette, without a transparent entry</li>
<li>"default80": an 80 color palette</li>
</ul>
These color palettes can be used with the "selectInputColor" Apache Trinidad tag.
</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="#{requestContext.formatter}">

<p>The EL expression <code>#{requestContext.formatter}</code> returns an
object that can be used for applying message formatting.  For
example, the following EL expression:
<source><![CDATA[    <h:outputText value="#{requestContext.formatter['One{0}Three']['Two']}"/>]]></source>

... will result in the output:

<source><![CDATA[OneTwoThree]]></source>
At this time, the "formatter" can only support formatting messages
containing a single parameter.
</p>
      </subsection>

    <subsection name="#{requestContext.agent}">

<p>The EL expression <code>#{requestContext.agent}</code> returns an object that describes the client agent that is making the request and is to display the rendered output. The agent object describes the following, 
  <ul>
    <li>agent type: Possible values "desktop", "pda", "phone" and "unknown"</li>
    <li>agent name and version: Agent names include "ie", "gecko" (for all gecko based browsers including Mozilla, Firefox, and Netscape 6+ versions), "webkit" (for all webkit based browsers including safari), "netfront", "blazer"</li>
    <li>platform name and version: Platform names include "windows", "linux", "mac", "palm", "solaris", "ppc"</li>
    <li>(mobile) device make and model when available, and</li> 
    <li>capabilities : Capability names include 
        <ul>
          <li>"dom" : dom level support (possible values are "none", "level1", "level2")</li>
          <li>"tables" : table layout support (possible values "basic", "advanced")</li>
          <li>"frames" : frames support (boolean value, "true" or "false"</li>
          <li>"iframes" : iframes support (boolean value, "true" or "false"</li>
          <li>"width" and "height" : screen resolution of the (mobile) device (integer value)</li>
        </ul>
    </li>
  </ul>
</p>
      </subsection>

    </section>
    
  </body>
</document>


