<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!--
    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
    or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information
    regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
    to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
    "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.
	   
-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Using the Apache Trinidad Component</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Using the Apache Trinidad Component">
      <p>
        <ul>
          <li><a href="#Introduction">Introduction</a></li>
          <li><a href="#The Table Model">The Table Model</a></li>
          <li><a href="#Columns">Columns</a>
            <ul>
              <li><a href="#Headers">Headers</a></li>
              <li><a href="#Data">Data</a></li>
              <li><a href="#Formatting">Formatting</a></li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li><a href="#Selection">Selection</a></li>
          <li><a href="#Sorting">Sorting</a>
            <ul>
              <li><a href="#SortEvent">SortEvent</a></li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li><a href="#Grid Lines and Banding">Grid Lines and Banding</a></li>
        </ul>
      </p>
    </section>


    <section name="Introduction">
      <P>
        The Apache Trinidad component is used to display a list of structured data.
        For example, if we have a data structure called Person that has two
        properties - firstname and lastname, we could use a Table with two
        columns - one for firstname, and the other for lastname - to display
        a list of Person objects.
      </P>
      <P>
        The Table component is similar to the standard <code>UIData</code>
        component in JSF, but includes a number of extra features,  including
        support for identifying rows by key (instead of by index),
        built-in support for paging through large models,
        sorting the model, and selecting single or multiple items in
        the model.
      </P>
    </section>

    <section name="The Table Model">
      <P>
        The Apache Trinidad component uses a model to access the data in the underlying list.
        The specific model class is
        <code>org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.model.CollectionModel</code>. You may
        also use other model instances, e.g., <code>java.util.List</code>,
        array, and <code>javax.faces.model.DataModel</code>. The Table will
        automatically convert the instance into a CollectionModel.
      </P>
      <P>
        To access a particular row in the list, first make that row current,
        and then call the <code>getRowData()</code> method on the Table. To
        make a row current, call the <code>setRowIndex(...)</code> method (on
        the Table) with the appropriate index into the list. Alternatively,
        call the <code>setRowKey(...)</code> method with the appropriate rowKey.      </P>
      <P>
        To obtain the total number of rows in the list, call the
        <code>getRowCount()</code> method on the Table. In the case where the
        model does not yet know the total number of rows that are
        available, <code>getRowCount()</code> will return -1.
      </P>
      <P>
        The Table has an <code>isRowAvailable()</code> method that returns
        <code>true</code> if the current row ( see <code>setRowIndex(...)</code> )
        is available. This method is especially useful when the total number
        of rows is unknown.
      </P>
    </section>

    <section name="Columns">
      <P>
        The immediate children of a Table component must all be
        <code>&lt;tr:column&gt;</code> components. Each visible ADF Column
        component creates a separate column in the Table.
      </P>
      <subsection name="Headers">
        <P>
          Use the "header" facet on a Column to create the column header. You
          can also use the "headerText" attribute to set the column header.
          The following example creates a two-column table with the column
          headers - "Firstname" and "Lastname":
        </P>
        <source><![CDATA[
<tr:table>
  <tr:column>
    <f:facet name="header">
      <tr:outputText value="Firstname"/>
    </f:facet>
    ...
  </tr:column>
  <tr:column headerText="Lastname">
    ...
  </tr:column>
</tr:table>]]>
        </source>
        <p>
Note that both ADF Faces and JSF HTML tags can be used inside of
the ADF table.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Data">
        <P>
          The child components of each Column display the data for each row in
          that column. The Column does not create child components per row;
          instead, each child is repeatedly rendered (stamped) once per
          row. Because of this stamping behavior, some components many
          not work inside the table.  Anything that is just pure output,
	  with no behavior, will work without problems, as will components that
          don't "mutate" even as they deliver events (for example,
          command components are fine).  Components that mutate
          their state are affected, but any that implement 
          EditableValueHolder are supported (this includes all
          form input controls from the JSF specification as well
          as ADF Faces input controls), as are UIXShowDetail components.
        </P>
        <P>
          As each row is stamped, the data for the current row ( see
          <code>getRowData()</code> ) is copied into an EL reachable property.
          The name of this property is defined by the <code>var</code>
          property on the Table. Once the Table has completed rendering, this
          property is removed (or reverted back to its previous value). In
          the following example, the data for each row is placed under the EL
          property "row". Each Column displays the data for each row by getting
          further properties from the "row" property:
        </P>
        <source><![CDATA[
<tr:table var="row" value="#{myBean.allEmployees}">
  <tr:column>
    <tr:outputText value="#{row.firstname}"/>
  </tr:column>
  <tr:column>
    tr:outputText value="#{row.lastname}"/>
  </tr:column>
</tr:table>]]>
        </source>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Formatting">
        <p>
          The Column component supports the following attributes related to
          formatting:
          <dl>
            <dt>align</dt>

            <dd>The type of alignment to use for this column. The legal
              values are "left", "right", "start", "end" and "center".
              Use "left" for left-justified, "right" for
              right-justified, and "center" for center-justified columns.
              For BiDi columns use "start" and "end".
              Use "start" (instead of "left") to left-align columns in a
              left-to-right locale, and right-align columns in a right-to-left
              locale.
              Similarly, use "end" (instead of "right") to
              right-align columns in a
              left-to-right locale, and left-align columns in a right-to-left
              locale.
            </dd>

            <dt>width</dt>
            <dd>The width of this column, e.g. "100px".
            </dd>

            <dt>noWrap</dt>
            <dd>Controls whether long lines of text in the column data should
            be wrapped.</dd>
          </dl>
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Column Groups">
            <P>
              <code>&lt;tr:column&gt; </code> tags can be nested to produce
              groups of columns. The header of a column group spans across
              all the columns it contains. The following example creates
              a column group that has the header "Name" and contains
              two sub columns with headers "First" and "Last":
            </P>
          <source><![CDATA[
  <tr:table var="row" value="#{myBean.employees}">
    <tr:column headerText="Name">
      <tr:column headerText="First">
        <tr:outputText value="#{row.firstname}"/>
      </tr:column>
      <tr:column headerText="Last">
        tr:outputText value="#{row.lastname}"/>
      </tr:column>
    </tr:column>
  </tr:table>]]>
          </source>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Row Headers">
        <P>
          Columns can be rendered as row headers by setting the
          "rowHeader" attribute on &lt;column&gt; to be true.
          Row header columns must be the first columns in a table.
        </P>
      </subsection>
    </section>

    <section name="Range Navigation">
      <P>
        When the list being displayed by a Table is huge, you can enable the Table 
        to break up the list into ranges and display a single range at a time. 
        Range controls are provided on the Table to let the user scroll to the next range, 
        or to go back to the previous range. If the total size of the list is known, a 
        control to let the user jump directly to a particular part of the list is also 
        provided on the Table. Use the Table attributes "rows" and "first" to control the 
  range navigation feature.
      </P>
      <P>
        The maximum number of rows to display in a single range is controlled
        by the "rows" attribute, which defaults to a reasonable size (e.g.,
        25). To disable range navigation (and display all the rows on one
        page) set this attribute to 0. In the following example, the maximum
        number of rows to display per range is set to 10: 
        <source>&lt;tr:table rows="10" ...&gt;</source>
      </P>
      <P>
        The current range to display is controlled by the "first"
        attribute. This attribute is an index (based at zero) of a row in the
        list. Each range starts with the row identified by "first", and only
        contains as many rows as indicated by the "rows" attribute. Initially,
        the "first" attribute defaults to zero, which displays the range 
        with the first row at the top.
      </P>
      <subsection name="RangeChangeEvent">
        <P>
          When the user changes the range (being displayed in the Table), the
          Table generates a <code>RangeChangeEvent</code>. This event includes the
          index (based at zero) of the row that should now be at the top of the
          range. The Table responds to this event by automatically changing the
          value of the "first" attribute to this index.
        </P>
        <P>
          In some cases it is necessary to know when the user changes the range
          on the Table (e.g., when the user navigates forward it might be necessary
          to release any cached data created for a previous range). To receive
          notifications of when the user changes the range, a
          <code>RangeChangeListener</code> instance should be registered with the
          Table. This is done by calling the <code>addRangeChangeListener</code>
          method, or by using the <code>rangeChangeListener</code> MethodBinding on the Table.
          These listeners are called after the Table has changed the
          "first" attribute in response to the event.
        </P>
      </subsection>
    </section>

    <section name="Displaying Details">
      <P>
        You can configure the Table to display or hide additional details of a
        particular row in response to a user gesture. When the details feature
        is enabled, a new column containing a toggle (per row) will render in
        the Table. When a toggle is activated, the details for that row are
        displayed. When a toggle is deactivated, the details for the row are
        hidden. The user can also display or hide the details for all rows at
        the same time (the controls for this feature are enabled by setting
        the "allDetailsEnabled" property to true.)
      </P>
      <P>
        To enable the details feature set the "detailStamp" facet on the
        Table. Place the components that are used to show the details (of a
        row), inside this facet. In the following example, the Person's age is
        displayed in the details section:

        <source><![CDATA[
<tr:table var="row" value="#{myBean.allEmployees}">
  <f:facet name="detailStamp">
    <tr:outputText value="#{row.age}"/>
  </f:facet>
</tr:table>]]>
        </source>
      </P>
      <P>
        Usually, the default behavior of the Table (with respect to displaying
        and hiding details) is sufficient. In some cases, however, it might be
        desirable to programmatically display or hide the details for a
        particular row. This can be done via the <code>RowKeySet</code> object
        obtained from the Table by calling the
        <code>getDisclosureState()</code> method. First, make the relevant row
        current by calling <code>setRowIndex(...)</code> or
        <code>setRowKey(...)</code> on the Table, and then call
        <code>add()</code> or <code>remove()</code> on the
        <code>RowKeySet</code> object. Adding the row to the set displays
        the details of the row. Removing the row hides them.
      </P>
      <subsection name="RowDisclosureEvent">
        <P>
          When the user hides or shows the details of a row, the Table
          generates a <code>RowDisclosureEvent</code>. This event has
          properties that return which rows were disclosed and which were
          undisclosed. The Table responds to this by expanding or collapsing
          the details of those rows.
        </P>
        <p>
          You can register custom <code>RowDisclosureListener</code> instances
          (that can do post processing) on the Table component.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>

    <section name="Selection">
      <p>
        The selection feature of a Table lets the user select one or more rows
        in the list. The user can then perform some operation on the selected
        rows by activating an appropriate ActionSource component (e.g., by
        clicking on an ADF CommandButton). Use the "rowSelection" attribute on
        the Table to enable the selection feature (see the examples below).
      </p>
      <p>
        There are two types of selection - single and multiple. The type of
        selection is determined by the value of the "selection" attribute.
        Use the value "single" to enable single selection, and "multiple" to
        enable multiple selection.
      </p>
      <P>
        The current selection of rows on the Table can be programmatically
        inspected and modified via the <code>RowKeySet</code> object obtained
        by calling <code>getSelectedRowKeys()</code> on the Table. To
        programmatically change a selection, add or remove rowKeys from this
        Set. Alternatively, the appropriate row can be made current by calling
        <code>setRowIndex(...)</code> or <code>setRowKey(...)</code> on the
        Table, and then the selection of that row may be changed by calling
        <code>add()</code> or <code>remove()</code> on the
        <code>RowKeySet</code>.
      </P>
      <subsection name="Selection Example">
        <P>
          In the following example, the <code>performDelete</code> method is
          called when the "Delete" button is clicked.
        </P>
        <source><![CDATA[
<tr:table binding="#{mybean.table}" rowSelection="multiple" ...>
  <f:facet name="footer">
      <tr:commandButton text="Delete" actionListener="#{mybean.performDelete}"/>
  </f:facet>
  ...
</tr:table>]]>
        </source>
        <P>
          The <code>performDelete</code> method iterates through all the
          selected rows and calls the <code>markForDeletion()</code> method on
          each one:
        </P>
        <source>
public void performDelete(ActionEvent action)
{
  UIXTable table = getTable();
  Iterator selection = table.getSelectedRowKeys().iterator();
  Object oldKey = table.getRowKey();
  while(selection.hasNext())
  {
    Object rowKey = selection.next();
    table.setRowKey(rowKey);
    MyRowImpl row = (MyRowImpl) table.getRowData();
    row.markForDeletion();
  }
  // restore the old key:
  table.setRowKey(oldKey);
}

// Binding methods for access to the table.
public void setTable(UIXTable table) { _table = table; }
public UIXTable getTable() { return _table; }
private UIXTable _table;
        </source>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="SelectionEvent">
        <P>
          The &lt;tr:table&gt; component triggers SelectionEvents when
          the selection state is changed. The SelectionEvent
          reports which rows were just deselected and which rows were just
          selected. Listeners for this event may be registered on the table
          using the "selectionListener" attribute or by adding the listener to
          the table using the "addSelectionListener" method.
        </P>
      </subsection>
    </section>

    <section name="Sorting">
      <p>
        The Table component supports sorting columns in ascending or
        descending order. A special UI indicator on a column header lets the
        user know that the column is sortable. When the user clicks on a
        column header to sort a previously unsorted column, the Table sorts
        the column data in ascending order. Subsequent clicks on the same
        header sort the data in the reverse order.
      </p>
      <p>
        There are three requirements to enable sorting: the underlying table
        model must support sorting, the "sortProperty" and "sortable"
        attributes must be set on the column to enable the sort capability for
        that column.
      </p>
      <P>
        To support sorting, the <code>CollectionModel</code> instance must implement the following methods:</P>
        <source>
public boolean isSortable(String propertyName)
public List getSortCriteria()
public void setSortCriteria(List criteria)
        </source>
      <P>
        If the underlying model is not a <code>CollectionModel</code>, the
        Table automatically examines the actual data to determine which
        properties are sortable. Any column that has data that implements
        <code>java.lang.Comparable</code> are sortable.  This automatic
        support cannot be nearly as efficient as coding sorting directly into
        a <code>CollectionModel</code> (for instance, by translating the sort
        into an "ORDER BY" SQL clause), but is sufficient for small data sets.
      </P>
      <P>
        To associate a column with a particular property-name to be used for
        sorting purposes, use the "sortProperty" attribute on the column.
        To enable the UI for sorting a particular column, set the
        "sortable" property to <code>true</code>.
      </P>
      <P>
        In the following example,
        both columns are sortable. Sorting the first column sorts by the
        "firstname" property; sorting the second column sorts by the "lastname"
        property.
      </P>
      <source><![CDATA[
<tr:table ...>
  <tr:column sortProperty="firstname" sortable="true">
    <f:facet name="header">
      <tr:outputText value="Firstname" />
    </f:facet>
    ...
  </tr:column>
  <tr:column>
    <f:facet name="header" sortProperty="lastname" sortable="true">
      <tr:outputText value="Lastname" />
    </f:facet>
    ...
  </tr:column>
</tr:table>]]>
      </source>

      <subsection name="SortEvent">
        <p>
          When the user clicks a sortable column header, the
          <code>&lt;tr:table&gt;</code> component generates a
          <code>SortEvent</code>. This event has a
          <code>getSortCriteria()</code> property that returns the criteria
          that the table must be sorted by.
        </p>
        <p>
          The Table responds to this event by calling the
          <code>setSortCriteria</code> method on the underlying
          <code>CollectionModel</code>. Any registered
          <code>SortListener</code> instances will also be called.
        </p>
      </subsection>

    </section>

    <section name="Grid Lines and Banding">
      <P>
        By default, the table draws both horizontal and vertical grid lines.
        These may be independently turned off by setting the
        "horizontalGridVisible" and/or "verticalGridVisible" attributes to
        "false".
      </P>
      <P>
        Banding is a technique where groups of rows (or columns)
        are displayed with alternating background colors. This helps to
        differentiate between adjacent groups of rows (or columns).
      </P>
      <P>
        The "rowBandingInterval" attribute on the Table controls how many
        consecutive rows form a row group (for the purposes of banding). If
        this is "0" all rows will have the same background color. If this is a
        positive number then adjacent row groups will have different
        background colors.
      </P>
      <P>
        The "columnBandingInterval" attribute on the Table controls how many
        columns form a column group (for the purposes of banding). If this is
        "0" all columns will have the same background color. If this is a
        positive number then adjacent column groups will have different
        background colors.
      </P>
      <P>
        In the following example, the row banding pattern is to have two rows
        with a light background, followed by two rows with a dark
        background. The pattern is repeated across all rows. Similarly the
        column banding pattern is to have alternating light/dark columns.
      </P>
      <source><![CDATA[
<tr:table rowBandingInterval="2" columnBandingInterval="1" ...>
  ...
</tr:table>]]>
      </source>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
