<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!--
    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
    or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information
    regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
    to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
    "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
    software distributed under the License is distributed on an
    "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
    KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
    specific language governing permissions and limitations
    under the License.
	   
-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Using the Apache Trinidad Tree Component</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Using the Apache Trinidad Tree Component">
      <p>
        <ul>
          <li><a href="#Introduction">Introduction</a></li>
          <li><a href="#The Tree Model">The Tree Model</a></li>
          <li><a href="#Tree">Tree</a>
            <ul>
              <li><a href="#Data">Data</a></li>
              <li><a href="#RowDisclosureEvent">RowDisclosureEvent</a></li>
              <li><a href="#SelectionEvent">SelectionEvent</a></li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li><a href="#TreeTable">TreeTable</a>
            <ul>
              <li><a href="#RowDisclosureEvent - TreeTable">RowDisclosureEvent</a></li>
              <li><a href="#SelectionEvent - TreeTable">SelectionEvent</a></li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li><a href="#Expand/Collapse State">Expand/Collapse State</a></li>
          <li><a href="#Selection State">Selection State</a></li>
          <li><a href="#Grid Lines and Banding">Grid Lines and Banding</a></li>
        </ul>
      </p>
    </section>


    <section name="Introduction">
      <P>
        Apache Trinidad tree components are used to display hierarchical data. For
        example, if we have a personnel organization chart depicting all the
        direct reports under each employee, we could use a tree component to
        display this chart. Each element (employee) in the hierarchy may have
        any number of child elements (direct reports). In addition several
        parent elements may share the same child elements.
      </P>

      <P>
        Apache Trinidad currently provides two tree components: Tree and TreeTable. 
        The Apache Trinidad Tree component supports multiple root elements, and it has a
        simple user interface (UI) - each element in the Tree is appropriately indented to indicate
        its level in the hierarchy, and is connected to its parent.
        The features of the Tree component include mechanisms for expanding and
        collapsing portions of the hierarchy.
      </P>

      <P>
        The Apache Trinidad TreeTable component displays a hierarchy
        in a UI similar to an Apache Trinidad Table, and is more elaborate than the Tree component. TreeTable supports displaying columns of data per element in the hierarchy. The features of the TreeTable
        component include mechanisms for focusing in on subtrees (within the main
        tree), as well as expanding and collapsing elements in the hierarchy.
      </P>

      <P>
        We recommend that you familiarize yourself with the <a
        href="table.html">Table component</a> before reading the rest of this chapter.
      </P>
    </section>

    <section name="The Tree Model">
      <P>
        The Apache Trinidad tree components use a model to access the data in the
        underlying hierarchy.  The specific model class is
        <code>org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.model.TreeModel</code>.
        <code>TreeModel</code> extends <code>CollectionModel</code> (see <a
        href="table.html">Using Apache Trinidad Tables</a> for more information
        about the <code>CollectionModel</code>). In other words, the
        <code>TreeModel</code> is a collection of rows. It has an
        <code>isContainer</code> method that returns <code>true</code> if the
        current row contains child rows. The children of the current row can
        be accessed by calling the <code>enterContainer</code> method. Once
        this method is called the <code>TreeModel</code> instance will change
        to be a collection of the child rows. To jump back up to the parent
        collection, call the <code>exitContainer</code> method.
      </P>

      <P>
        You may find the
        <code>org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.model.ChildPropertyTreeModel</code> class
        useful when constructing a <code>TreeModel</code>.
      </P>

    </section>

    <section name="Tree">
      <P>
        The Tree component displays a multi-root hierarchy in a simple UI
        where each element in the hierarchy is indented relative to
        the corresponding parent element.
      </P>

      <subsection name="Data">
        <P>
          The Tree uses a stamping strategy similar to the Apache Trinidad Table
          component.  The "nodeStamp" facet of the Tree is used to display the
          data for each element in the tree. The Tree does not create
          components per element; instead, the "nodeStamp" is repeatedly
          rendered (stamped) once per element. Because of this stamping
          behavior, only certain types of components are supported as
          children inside a Tree. Supported components include all
          components with no behavior and most components that implement the
          ValueHolder or ActionSource interfaces.
        </P>
        <P>
          Each time the "nodeStamp" is stamped, the data for the current
          element (see <code>getRowData()</code> in <a href="table.html">Using
          Apache Trinidad Tables</a>) is copied into an EL reachable property.  The
          name of this property is defined by the <code>var</code> property on
          the Tree. Once the Tree has completed rendering, this property is
          removed (or reverted back to its previous value). In the following
          example, the data for each element is placed under the EL property
          "node". The "nodeStamp" displays the data for each element by
          getting further properties from the "node" property:
        </P>
        <source><![CDATA[
<tr:tree var="node">
  <f:facet name="nodeStamp">
    <tr:outputText value="#{node.firstname}"/>
  </f:facet>
</tr:tree>]]>
        </source>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="RowDisclosureEvent">
        <P>
          The Tree renders expand/collapse icons that the user can click on to
          expand or collapse a subtree. When these icons are clicked, the Tree
          generates a <code>RowDisclosureEvent</code>. This event has two <code>
          RowKeySet</code> objects. One, called RemovedSet, for all the collapsed
          nodes and one, called AddedSet, for all the expanded nodes. The Tree 
          expands the subtrees under all nodes in the added set and collapses the
          subtrees under all nodes in the removed set.
        </P>
        <p>
          You can register custom <code>RowDisclosureListener</code> instances
          (that can do post processing) on the Tree component.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="SelectionEvent">
        <P>
          The Tree supports a <code>rowSelection</code> attribute. Valid
          values for the <code>rowSelection</code> attribute are: single, multiple,
          and none. If a Tree is selectable, clicking on a node causes the tree to 
          highlight the node and render it as selected. ctrl-click and shift-click
          operations are supported for trees which support multiple selections. 
          When nodes are selected/unselected, the Tree fires a <code>SelectionEvent
          </code>. This event has two <code>RowKeySet</code> objects. One, called 
          RemovedSet, for all the unselected nodes and one, called AddedSet, 
          for all the selected nodes.
        </P>
        <p>
          You can register custom <code>SelectionListener</code> instances
          (that can do post processing) on the Tree component.
        </p>
      </subsection>

    </section>
    
    <section name="TreeTable">
      <P>
        The TreeTable component displays a hierarchy in a UI 
        similar to Table. Like the Table, the TreeTable's children must be Apache Trinidad
        Column components (Please see <a
        href="table.html#Columns">Table Columns</a>). Like the Tree, the TreeTable has a "nodeStamp"
        facet which renders the "Object Name" Column. The TreeTable has a
        "pathStamp" facet for rendering the focus path.
      </P>
      <P>
        The "Object Name" Column contains the primary identifier of an element
        in the hierarchy. For example, in an organization chart of employees, the "Object Name"
        Column might be the employee name.
      </P>
      <P>
        The TreeTable supports the same stamping behavior as the
        Tree component. In the following example, The "Object Name" Column is
        the "Employee Name" Column. For each element (that is, employee) the
        TreeTable stamps out the name, ID and the department.
      </P>
      <source><![CDATA[
<tr:treeTable var="node">
  <f:facet name="nodeStamp">
    <tr:column>
      <f:facet name="header">
        <tr:outputText value="Employee Name"/>
      </f:facet>
      <tr:outputText value="#{node.ename}"/>
    </tr:column>
  </f:facet>
  <f:facet name="pathStamp">
    <tr:outputText value="#{node.ename}"/>
  </f:facet>
  <tr:column>
    <f:facet name="header">
      <tr:outputText value="Employee Id"/>
    </f:facet>
    <tr:outputText value="#{node.empid}"/>
  </tr:column>
  <tr:column>
    <f:facet name="header">
      <tr:outputText value="Department"/>
    </f:facet>
    <tr:outputText value="#{node.dname}"/>
  </tr:column>
</tr:treeTable>]]>
      </source>
      <P>
        The TreeTable supports all the formatting properties that are supported by the
        Column component.  Please see <a
        href="table.html#Columns">Using Apache Trinidad Tables</a> for more
        information about the Apache Trinidad Column component.
      </P>

     <subsection name="FocusEvent">  	 
        <P> 	 
          In addition to displaying expand/collapse icons, the TreeTable also 	 
          renders a column containing "focus" icons that a user can click to 	 
          focus on (or zoom into) a particular element's subtree of children. 	 
        </P> 	 
        <p> 	 
          To focus (or zoom) out of a subtree, the user can click on 	 
          path links that are rendered above the TreeTable. These path links 	 
          are rendered by the "pathStamp" facet. If this facet is not provided 	 
          the focus column and the path links are not rendered. 	 
        </p> 	 
        <P> 	 
          The TreeTable has a "focusPath" property that controls which element 	 
          has the current focus. This property is a 	 
          <code>java.util.List</code> of row-keys that describe a path from 	 
          the root to the element that has the focus. 	 
        </P> 	 
        <P> 	 
          When the user focuses in or out, the TreeTable generates a 	 
          <code>FocusEvent</code>. The element that the user focused in, is 	 
          made current before the event is delievered. The TreeTable responds 	 
          to this event by modifying the "focusPath" property appropriately. 	 
          Subsequently, any registered <code>FocusListener</code> instances 	 
          are called. 	 
        </P> 	 
      </subsection>

     <subsection name="DisclosureAllEvent">
        <P> 	 
          The TreeTable allows the user to expand or collapse all the subtrees 	 
          by clicking on special "expand-all" or "collapse-all" links. In 	 
          response to this, the TreeTable generates a 	 
          <code>DisclosureAllEvent</code>. This event has an 	 
          <code>isExpandAll</code> method that returns whether the user wants 	 
          to show or hide all the subtrees. 	 
        </P> 	 
        <P>
          The TreeTable responds to this by expanding or collapsing all the
          elements under the current focus root. If the tree is massive, the
          expand-all operation will not propagate beyond the children of the
          current focus root.
        </P>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="RowDisclosureEvent - TreeTable">
        <P>
          Like the Tree component the TreeTable generates a
          <code>RowDisclosureEvent</code>. Please see the Tree's <a
          href="#RowDisclosureEvent">RowDisclosureEvent</a> description for more
          information about this event.
        </P>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="SelectionEvent - TreeTable">
        <P>
          Like the Tree component the TreeTable generates a
          <code>SelectionEvent</code>. Please see the Tree's <a
          href="#SelectionEvent">SelectionEvent</a> description for more
          information about this event.
        </P>
      </subsection>

    </section>

    <section name="Expand/Collapse State">
      <P>
        The Apache Trinidad tree components use an instance of the
        <code>org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.model.RowKeySet</code> class to keep track
        of which elements are expanded. This instance is stored as the
        "disclosedRowKeys" attribute on the component. You may use this instance to
        programmatically control the expand/collapse state of an element in
        the hierarchy. Any element contained by the <code>RowKeySet</code>
        instance is deemed expanded. All other elements are collapsed.  This
        class also supports operations like <code>addAll()</code> and
        <code>removeAll()</code>.
      </P>
    </section>

    <section name="Selection State">
      <P>
        The Apache Trinidad tree components use an instance of the
        <code>org.apache.myfaces.trinidad.model.RowKeySet</code> class to keep track
        of which elements are selected. This instance is stored as the
        "selectedRowKeys" attribute on the component. You may use this instance to
        programmatically control the selection state of an element in
        the hierarchy. Any element contained by the <code>RowKeySet</code>
        instance is deemed selected. All other elements are not selected.  This
        class also supports operations like <code>addAll()</code> and
        <code>removeAll()</code>.
      </P>

    </section>

    <section name="Grid Lines and Banding">
        Like the Table component, the TreeTable component supports vertical and horizontal
        grid lines and banding. Please see <a
        href="table.html#Grid Lines and Banding">Table Grid Lines and Banding</a> for more
        information.
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
